We just started a new unit on graph theory, which
is going to be our focus for the next couple
lectures in 6 .006. And so I thought we'd give a
little bit of review at the beginning of lecture,
because as usual, I muddled together a
lot of notions in our previous lecture.
And then start with some new ideas. So basically,
in our previous lecture, we talked about an
algorithm called
breadth -first search.
And then almost always, you see that paired with
the second algorithm called depth -first search.
And following tradition and basically logic,
we'll do the same thing in 006 today. But in any
event, for today, we'll stick to the technical
material. So a little bit of review. I guess
actually the one thing I didn't do on this slide
was actually draw a graph. So we should probably
start with that. So if you recall, graph is a
collection of nodes or vertices depending, I don't
know, is it like a European
-American thing or something, and edges.
So here's an example, which as usual, I'm not
managing to draw particularly clearly. So this graph
is kind of like a cycle. So I have directed edges
here, here, here, and here. And of course, there
are many kind of variations on the theme. So our
basic sort of definition of a graph is that we
have some set v, which is
like the set of vertices.
And then we have a set
e, which is set of edges.
And this is a subset of v cross v. And this is
nothing more than fancy notation for saying that an
edge is a pair of vertices, right, like a from
and a to vertex. Of course, there are many
variations on this theme. You could have a
directed versus an undirected graph. So this one is
directed, meaning the edges look like arrows.
They didn't have arrowheads. They'd be undirected.
We defined something called a simple graph, where
you have essentially no repeated edges. So for
instance, you can't do something like
this, where you have the same edge twice.
And then there are a couple of different
definitions that were kind of useful, right? So in
particular, I'm
going to erase this
useless edge here.
Maybe make my graph slightly more
interesting. So I'll add another
edge going in the reverse direction. So maybe I
have, I'm going to give my vertices labels x, y,
z, and w.
Then we talked about the neighbors of a given
vertex, which are the vertices that you can reach by
following edges in or out of your vertex, right?
So in particular, the outgoing neighbors, which we
sort of implicitly defined in our
previous lecture but didn't call it out,
we're going to notate with adj plus. And these
are all of the things that you can reach by going
out of a vertex into the
next one. So for example,
adj plus of w is going to be the set of vertices.
Well, notice I can get from w to y and also from
w to z. Yeah, so, nope,
nope, y comma z.
OK.
So to continue just our tiny amount of review for
the day, remember that a graph, there are many
different ways to represent a graph. The sort of
brain dead one would be just like a big long list
of edges. But of course, for our algorithms,
that's not a particularly efficient way to check
things like, does this
edge exist in my graph?
So the basic representation that I think we're
mostly working from in this course is to think of a
graph like a set of vertices, each of which maps
to another set of vertices. So roughly every
vertex maybe stores its outgoing set of edges,
right? And so this is kind of nice because, of
course, very quickly, we can answer questions
like, is this edge inside of our graph? Or we can
iterate over the neighbors of a vertex and so on,
which are the kind of typical things that we do
in a lot of graph algorithms.
And then finally, in our previous lecture, we
started talking about paths, right? So a path is like
a chain of vertices that can get me from one vertex
to the other only following edges of my graph.
There was a term that I think I forgot to define
last time because it didn't really matter a ton,
which is a simple path, which is just a path
that doesn't have the same vertex more than one.
And then, of course, there are many different
questions you could ask about a graph that are
basically different problems involving computing
paths, right? So for instance, the shortest path
between two vertices is sort of our canonical one
in graph theory. Or you could ask questions about
reachability and so on. So there's our
basic review from our previous lecture.
Does our course staff have any
questions about things so far?
Excellent. OK. And there's one additional piece
of terminology that I fudged a little bit into. A
little bit last time, or rather, my co -instructor
suggested a bit of an attitude adjustment. So I
thought I'd better clarify really quick. There's
this interesting phrase, linear time, which we all
know and love in computer science theory. And
the sort of implicit thing, especially in this
course, is that when we say linear time, we mean
in the size of the input, right? And so if we have
a linear time graph algorithm, well, how much space
does it take to store a graph? Well, we need a
list of vertices and a list
of edges, if nothing else.
And the way we interpret this phrase, linear time,
is that it's an algorithm that looks like what
we've shown on the screen, right? The time is
proportional to maybe the sum of the number of
vertices and the number of edges. If that makes
you uncomfortable, like it does for me, because one
of these can kind of scale on the other, I think
it's always fine to add more detail, right? So if
you want to say linear in the sum of the number
of vertices and edges, that's perfectly fine. But
if you see this phrase, that's how you should
interpret it. Hopefully, that's a fair way to put it.
Excellent.
OK, so last time, we talked about an algorithm
called breadth -first search, BFS, for those in the
know. Breadth -first search is an algorithm. And
the reason we use the word breadth is because it's
kind of, remember, we talked about level sets
last time, because we talked about breadth -first
search in the context of computing shortest paths.
And in particular, we have our source node all
the way on the left -hand side. And then breadth
-first search constructed all the nodes that were
distance 1 away, right?
That's the first level set.
Then all the distance 2 away, and then all the
distance 3 away, and so on, right? So in particular,
the level set L3 isn't visited until
we're completely done with level set L2.
Today, we're going to define another algorithm,
which is called depth -first search, which doesn't
do that, but rather starts with the source vertex
and just starts walking all the way out until it
can't do that anymore, and then kind of
backtracks. It's one way to think about it.
And so somehow, in breadth -first search, we're
drawing concentric circles. In depth -first search,
we're doing the opposite. We're extruding outward
until we reach the outer boundary and then
exploring a graph that way. OK, and these are
sort of the two extremes in terms of graph search
kind of techniques that are typically used under
the basic building blocks for algorithms in graph
theory. So in order to motivate and think about
depth -first search, we're going to define a second
problem, which is closely related to shortest
path, but not exactly the same. And that's the
reachability problem.
So here, I have the world's
simplest directed graph.
Edges and the circles are
the nodes or the vertices.
And I've marked one special node in
blue, and his name is the source node.
And now, the question I want to ask is, what are
all of the other nodes in my graph that I can
reach by following edges, directed edges, starting
with the source? So obviously, I can get to the
node in the lower right, no problem. And of course,
once I get there, I can traverse an edge upward
to get to that
second green vertex.
Notice that I was really sneaky and evil, and I
drew edges in this graph that might make you think
that the red node is reachable, the red one being
on the upper left. I'm realizing now that for
colorblind people,
this isn't a great slide.
But of course, because all the edges from the
red vertex on the left here point out, I can't
actually reach it from
the blue source node.
So the reachability problem is just asking,
which nodes can I reach from a given source?
Pretty straightforward, I think. Of course, there
are many ways to solve this, right? In fact, one
way we could do it would be to use our previous
lecture, right? We could compute the shortest path
distance from the source to all the other nodes.
And then what would the length of the shortest
path from the source to an unreachable node
be? Any thoughts from our audience here?
Infinity. Thank you,
Professor Domain.
Right. So in addition to this, of course, a
totally reasonable question, thinking back to our
shortest path lecture, there are sort of two queries
we might make, right? One is just, what is the
length of the shortest path? The other is, what
is the actual shortest path from the source to a
given vertex?
We could ask a very similar thing here, right?
Which is like, OK, you tell me that the green guy is
reachable, but how? Give me a path as evidence or
a certificate, if you want to be fancy about it.
So in order to do that, just like last time,
remember, we defined a particular data structure that
was the shortest path tree. We can do something
very similar here, right? In particular, this is
the extent of my
PowerPoint skill here.
If I have a reachability problem, I can additionally
store, I can decorate every node in my graph
with one other piece of information, which is
the previous node along some path from my source
to that thing, right? And just like last time, if
I want to get an actual path from the source to
w, what could I do? I can start with w and then
just keep following those parent relationships
until I get back to the source.
That list of vertices, I get a path
from the source to the target that's valid.
So this object is called a path tree, just like
we talk, or a parent tree, rather. Just like we
talked about in our last lecture, there's no reason
why this thing should ever have a cycle in it.
It's certainly a tree.
Right, so that's the basic reachability problem.
And in addition to that, we can compute this
object p, which is going to give me information
about how any given node was reachable. There's a
slight difference between the parent tree that
I've defined here and the shortest path tree, which
I defined last time, which is I'm not going to
require that the shortest path I get, or oh, man,
the path I get when I backtrack along my tree p is
the shortest path. It's just a path. Because for
the reachability problem, I actually don't care,
right? Like, I could have a weird, circuitous,
crazy long path, and it still
tells me that a node is reachable.
Right, so that's our basic setup and our data
structure. And now we can introduce a, problem to
solve reachability. Again, we already have an
algorithm for doing that, right, which is to compute
shortest paths.
And remember that our shortest path algorithm from
previous lecture took linear time and the size
of the input, right? It took v plus e time. Now
the question is, can we do a little better? The
answer, obviously, is yes, because I just asked
it and I gave you this problem. OK, and here's a
technique for doing that, which, unsurprisingly,
is a recursive algorithm. I'm going to swap my
notes for my handwritten notes.
And this algorithm is called death first
search. And here's the basic strategy.
I'm going to choose a source
node. I've labeled that node 1 here.
I suppose it actually would have made sense for me
to actually to 0 index this. Maybe in the slides
I'll fix it later. But in any event,
I'm going to mark my source node.
And now I'm going to look at every node, every edge
coming out of that node, and I'm going to visit
it recursively, right? So that's our sort
of for loop inside of this function visit.
And then for each neighboring node, if I haven't
visited it before, in other words, I currently
haven't given it a parent, right? That's our if
statement here. Then I'm going to say, well, now
they do have a parent, and that
parent is me. And I'm going to recurse.
You guys see what this is doing? It's kind of
crawling outward inside of our graph. So let's do the
example on the screen.
And I purposefully designed this experiment or
this example to look a little bit different from
breath first search, at least if you choose to do
the ordering that I did. So here's our graph. 1,
2, 5, 3, 4.
OK. And let's think about the traversal order
that the first search is going to do, right? So
here's our source.
And now what does the source do? So let's think
about a recursion tree. So we have the source all
the way up in here. And now he's going to
start calling the visit function recursively.
So and I'll go ahead and number
these the same as on the screen.
Well, he has one outgoing neighbor, and it hasn't
been visited yet. So of course, the very first
recursive call that I'll
make is to that neighbor 2.
Now the neighbor
2 also recurses.
Hopefully, this kind of schematic picture
makes some sense what I'm trying to draw here.
And well, now the 2 has two neighbors, right? A
3 and a 5. So let's say that we choose 3 first.
Well,
the 3 now recurses. He calls 4, and then the
recursion tree is kind of done. So now it goes back
out. And then finally,
well, now the 3 or oh, boy.
Yeah, the 2 looks at its next neighbor,
which is the 5, and visits that recursively.
Notice that this is not following the level sets,
right? The death first search algorithm got all
the way to the end of my tree in the recursive
calls and then kind of backed its way out to the 2
before calling the 5. These are not the same
technique. 1 goes all the way to the end and then kind
of backtracks. Whereas when I say backtrack, what
I mean is the recursion is kind of unraveling.
Whereas in breadth first search, I visit everything
in one level set before I work my way out. Does
that distinction make sense?
OK, so of course, we need to prove that this
algorithm does something useful. So let's do that now.
So in particular, we need a correctness
proof. So our claim is going to be.
Let's see here.
The depth first search algorithm
visits all, I guess, reachable v,
and that it correctly sets
the parent in the process.
OK, so in order to prove this, of course, as with
almost everything in this course, we're going to
use induction. And in particular, what we're going
to do is do induction on the distance from the
source. So we're going to say that for all vertices
in distance k from the source, this statement
is true. And then we're going to prove this
inductively on k. OK, so we want to do induction.
And then we're going to do
induction on k, which is the distance
to the source vertex. So as with all of our inductive
proofs, we have to do our base case and then
our inductive step.
So in the base case,
k equals 0. This is a hella easy case because, of
course, what is the thing that is distance 0 from
the source?
It's the source. Yeah? And take a look at our
strategy all the way at the top of this slide. We
explicitly set the correct parent for the source
and, in some sense, visit it because the very
first thing we do
is call visit of s.
So there's kind of nothing to say here. Yeah?
Well, there's plenty to say if you write it on your
homework, but your lazy instructor
is going to write a check mark here.
OK,
so now we have to do
our inductive step.
So what
does that mean?
It's true for all nodes within a distance k. And
then we're going to prove that our statement is
true for all nodes
within a distance k plus 1.
OK? So let's do that.
Let's consider a vertex v that's distance k plus
1 away. So in other words, the distance from the
source to v is
equal to k plus 1.
Right? And what's our goal? Our goal is to show
that the parent of v is set correctly. Yeah?
What was that?
Oh, sorry. I forgot that the distances in this
class are ordered. Yeah, that's absolutely right. So
it should be the
distance from s to v. Yeah.
Sorry, I'm really not used to thinking about
directed graphs, but that's a good fix.
OK, so now what can we do? Well,
this number is distance here. So in particular,
there's some shortest path from s to v.
So remember our argument last time, right, that
essentially when we look at shortest path and we
kind of truncate by 1, it's still a shortest path?
That property doesn't matter so much here, but
at least we know that there's another vertex on
the path, which is one distance, one less away.
So let's take u,
which is also a vertex,
to be the previous node
on the shortest path.
And so in particular, we know that the distance
from s to u is equal to k. And conveniently, of
course, by our inductive hypothesis here, we
know that our property is true for this guy.
OK, so now our algorithm, what do we know? Well,
because our property is true, the visit function
at some point in its life is called on this vertex
u. That's sort of what our induction assumes. So
we have two cases.
Right, so when we visit u,
we know
that when we call this visit function, well, remember
that v, kind of by definition, is in Adj plus
of u, right? So in particular,
DFS is going to consider v
when it gets called.
OK,
and now there's two cases,
right? So either when this happens,
p of v
does not equal none.
Right, well, what does that mean? Well, it means
that we already kind of found a suitable parent
for v and we're in good shape.
Otherwise,
p of v does equal none.
Well, in this case, the very next line of code
correctly sets the parent and we're all set. So in
both of these two cases, we show that the parent
of u was set correctly either by that line of code
right here or just previously.
And so in either case,
our induction is done.
I guess given the feedback I received from our
previous lecture, we now can end our LaTeX suitably.
OK, so what did we just show? We showed that the
death first search algorithm can dig around in a
graph and tell me all of the things that are
searchable or rather are reachable from a given source
just basically by calling visit on that
source and then expanding outward recursively.
OK, so I think this is certainly straightforward
from an intuitive perspective. It's easy to get
lost when you write these kind of formal induction
proofs. Because they always feel a tiny bit like
tautology. So you should go home and
kind of convince yourself that it's not.
OK, so of course, what do we do in this class?
We always follow the same kind of boring pattern.
The first thing we do, define an algorithm.
Second thing we do, make sure that it's the right
algorithm. What's the
third thing we need to do?
Analyze it. That's right. In particular, make
sure that it finishes before the heat death of the
universe. And indeed, death first search doesn't
really take all that long, which is a good thing.
So let's think about this a bit.
So what's going to end up
happening in death first search?
Well, we're going to visit every vertex
at most once, kind of by definition here.
And in each case, we're going to just visit its
neighboring edges. Can we ever traverse an edge
more than one time?
No, because the visit function only ever gets
called one time per vertex and our edges are
directed.
So kind of you think about the from of every edge,
the from vertex is only ever visited once. One
time and hence, every edge
is only visited one time.
Do we ever visit? Yes. Does DFS work for a
directed graph? An undirected graph, absolutely. So
there's sort of different ways to think about
it. One is to think of an undirected graph like a
directed graph with two edges pointed either way,
which I think is in this class how we actually
kind of notated it in
the previous lecture.
Yeah, actually, that's probably a reasonable
way to reduce it. So we'll stick with that.
Right.
Do we ever visit a vertex that
is not reachable from the source?
Well, the answer is no, right? Because all I ever
do is recursively call on my neighbors. And so
kind of by definition, if I'm not
reachable, DFS will never see it.
So if I think about my runtime carefully, it's not
quite the same as breadth first search. Remember
that breadth first
search took v plus e time.
In depth first search, it just takes order e time
because I'm expanding outward from the source
vertex, hitting every edge, adjacent to every
vertex that I've seen so far. But I never reach a
vertex that isn't reachable, right? And so because
this only ever touches every edge one time,
we're in good shape.
And I see a question here. Yeah. Does
BFS reach vertices that are not reachable?
Does BFS reach vertices
that are not reachable?
I guess not, now that you mention it. But at least
in my boring proof of order v time last time,
our very first step of BFS reserved space proportional
to v, which is enough to already make that
runtime correct. Good question. Yeah. So I guess
the way that we've talked about it where you
construct one level set after a time, if you
think of that as reachability, then no. It doesn't
reach it in the for loop. But just by construction
when we started, we already took the time that
we're talking about here.
So notice these runtimes aren't exactly the
same. So for example, if my graph has no edges,
BFS still is going to take time. Yeah. Because it
still has to take order v time, at least the way
in the sort of brain dead way that we've implemented
it last time. Obviously, in that case, we
could probably do
something better.
Whereas the way that we've defined the DFS algorithm,
it only takes edge time. I see confusion on
my instructor's
face. No. OK. Good.
The one thing to notice is that these are algorithms
for slightly different tasks in some sense,
right? The way that we wrote down breadth -first
search last time, conveniently, it gives us the
shortest path. There are breadth -first search
algorithms that doesn't. I think in this class, we
kind of think of breadth -first search, we motivate
it in terms of the shortest path problem. But
it's just kind of a strategy of
working outwards from a vertex.
Whereas here, the way we've written down depth
-first search, there's no reason why the path that
we get should be the shortest, right?
So to think of a really extreme example,
let's say that I
have a cycle graph.
Right. So I get a big loop. Like this. Let's say
that I do depth -first search starting from this
vertex. Well, what will happen? Well, this guy
will call its neighbor recursively, who will then
call its neighbor recursively, will then call his
neighbor recursively, and so on. So of course,
when I do depth -first search, when I get to this
vertex, there's a chain of one, two, three, four
vertices behind it.
Is that the shortest path from the source to the
target here? Well, clearly not, right? I could
have traversed that
edge. I just chose not to.
OK.
So that's the depth -first search algorithm. It's
just essentially a recursive strategy where I
traverse all my neighbors,
and each of my neighbors traverses their neighbors,
and so on. OK. So why might we want to use this
algorithm? Well, we've already solved the
reachability problem. So let's solve a few more things
using the same
basic strategy here.
So
there's some notions that we've sort of actually,
in some sense, already used in the lecture here,
but we might as well call them out for what
they are, which is this idea of connectivity.
So a graph is connected if there's a path
getting from every vertex to every other vertex.
Now, connectivity in a directed graph is kind of
a weird object. For instance, think of a directed
graph with just two edges,
and one edge goes from u to v.
Then I can get from v to u, but not
vice versa. That's kind of a weird notion.
So here, in 6 .006, we'll mostly worry about
connectivity only for undirected graphs, because the
vertices just basically come in big connected
clumps. Or the more technical term for a big
connected clump is a connected component. Yeah? So
let's see an example. So let's say that I have a
graph which has
an edge
and then a triangle.
This is one graph. Do you see that? There's a
collection of vertices, and there's a collection of
edges. But it has two connected components, the
guy on the right and the guy on the left, meaning
that each vertex here is reachable from every other
vertex here. Each vertex here is reachable from
every vertex here. But there's no edge that goes
from the triangle to the line segment. Yep? And so
in the connected components problem,
we're given a graph like this guy.
And initially, we don't, you know, OK, when I
draw it like this, it's pretty clear that my graph
has two connected components. Maybe my graph
embedding algorithm failed and it drew an edge like
that. Well, then maybe, I don't know. It's
still pretty obvious that there's two connected
components. But you can imagine a universe where
you don't know that a priori. And the problem
you're trying to solve is just to enumerate all
these clumps of vertices that are reachable from
one another in an
undirected graph.
And conveniently,
we can use depth -first search to solve this
problem pretty easily. Right? So how could we do it?
Well, in some sense,
how can we find one connected component? So let's
say that I just choose a vertex in my graph.
Well, what do I know about
everything in its connected component?
Well, it's reachable from that vertex. Remember,
we just solved the reachability problem, which
says if I have a vertex, I can now tell you all
the other vertices that are reachable from this
guy. Right? So I could call DFS on, well, any
vertex in this cycle here, call the reachability
thing.
It's one of two things. Right? Either the vertex
has a parent in that object P, or it's the source.
Right? So I could very easily find the connected
component corresponding to that vertex. Does that
make sense?
Have I found all the
connected components?
No. I found one. Right? I found the one corresponding
to the arbitrary vertex that I just chose.
So how could I fix this?
Well, it's super simple. I could put a for loop
on the outside, which just loops over all the
vertices, maybe.
But if I don't have a connected component
yet, then I need to make a new one.
So then I call DFS on that vertex. I collect all
the vertices that I got, and I iterate. So this is
the algorithm that, in this class, we're going to
call full DFS. By the way, you could do the same
thing with full breadth -first
search. That's perfectly fine,
just kind of by analogy here. Right. So
what is full DFS? Ooh, this chalk is easier.
Well, I'm going to iterate
over all my vertices.
So I'm going to do DFS,
where I stands for for loop.
Right? So if V is unvisited,
then I'm going to do DFS
starting at V. I guess we use visit to refer to
this in the previous slide. And that's going to
kind of flood fill that
whole connected component.
And then I can collect that
connected component and continue.
So I'm checking something to be visited to
somehow take a bunch of time and make my algorithm
slower than it needs to be. But of course, we have
a set data structure that we know can do that in
order one time, at
least in expectation.
So this is the
full DFS algorithm.
Well, it's DFS because I call DFS on every
vertex. It's full because I looped over all the
vertices.
Right. And so if we think about it, how much
time does this algorithm take? It's a little bit
sneaky because somehow I have a for loop over
all the vertices that I could imagine a universe
where I get vertices times some other number because
there's a for loop and then there's something
inside of it. I think that's how we're used
to thinking about runtime of for loops.
But in this case, that actually doesn't happen
because there's never a case where an edge gets
traversed more than one time. Because if I'm in
one connected component, then by definition, I
can't be in another
connected component.
And so what happens is, in some sense, this innocent
looking call to DFS, I suppose if you were a
Lisp programmer, you somehow wouldn't like this.
It has a side effect, which is that I marked all
the vertices in that connected
component as don't touch me again.
And so implicitly, I kind of removed edges in this
process. So if you think through it carefully,
the runtime of this full DFS algorithm is v plus
e time because every edge is touched no more than
one time.
Kind of amortized over all the different calls
to DFS here. And there's this for loop over
vertices. So there's clearly an order v that
you need here. Does that argument make sense?
So again, we call that linear in the size of the
input. I'm going to say it many times to get it in
my own head correctly.
OK. Right. So this is the basic problem. This
comes up all the time, by the way. It seems like
somehow a totally brain dead, weird algorithm.
Somehow, why would you want an algorithm that finds
connected components? Why would you even have a
graph that's disconnected or something? But of
course, that can happen a lot. So for instance,
maybe you work at a social media company and people
have friends. But Eric and I are friends, and we're
not friends with anybody else. We have a blood
oath kind of thing. Then that might be not so easy
to find in the graph because, of course, we're
just two among a sea of students in this classroom,
all of which have different interconnections
that are just enumerated based on the list of
edges. And so even though pictorially, it's kind of
hard to draw
a connected component algorithm in a way that
doesn't make it sound kind of like a useless
technique from the start because it's very clear
there are two connected components there, of
course, we still have to be able to
write code to solve this sort of thing.
OK. So for once, I think I'm
almost on time in lecture today.
So we have one additional application of depth
-first search in our class today. And that is a
graph called a D -Dag, which is sort of on the
opposite end of the spectrum. So we just talked
about graphs that are undirected and thinking
about cycles. Now, on the opposite end, we might
think of a DAG.
So a DAG is a
directed acyclic graph.
Can anybody think of a special case of a DAG? I
suppose I should define it first, and then we'll
come back to that question, which
means exactly what it sounds like.
So actually, the graph I gave you all the way at
the beginning of lecture, I think secretly was an
example of one of these.
So let's say that I
have directed edges.
Maybe if I make the head a triangle,
that's a little easier to see.
I'm not so sure. In any event, so I'm going to
have an edge up and an edge to the right, and
similarly an edge down
and an edge to the right.
This graph looks like a cycle. But it's not, because
the only direction that I can move is from the
left -hand side to the right -hand side. So this
is a directed graph. And it doesn't contain any
cycles, meaning there's no path that I can take
from a vertex that gets back to itself along the
directed edges.
And DAGs show up all the time. Now that I've defined
what a DAG is, can somebody give me an example
of a DAG that we've
already seen in 6 .006?
A tree, at least if we orient all the edges
kind of pointing downward in the tree. Yeah.
Otherwise, I guess it's kind of debatable whether
it's a DAG or not. If there's no direction to the
edges, then somehow the
definition just doesn't apply.
OK, so in processing directed acyclic graphs,
there's a really useful thing that you can do that's
going to show up in this class apparently quite
a bit, which is kind of interesting to me. I'm
curious to see what that looks like, which is to
compute a topological order on the graph where
topologies here. So as a geometry professor in my
day job, I get all excited. But in this case, a
topological order is a
fairly straightforward thing.
Actually, it's defined on the screen. And I have
bad handwriting anyway. So let's just stick with
that. So topological ordering, so we think of f
as a function that assigns maybe every node an
index in array. I guess I shouldn't use the word
array here, but just like an index in ordering. So
this is the first vertex. And
this is the second vertex, and so on.
Then a topological order is one that has the
property shown here, which is that if I have a
directed edge from u to v,
then f of u is less than
f of v. So in other words,
if I look at the ordering that I get in my
topological order, u has to appear before v.
So let's look at our example again. So let's
give our nodes names. So here's a, b, c, d.
Well, what clearly has to be the first node in my
topological order? a, right? Because it's all the
way on the left -hand side.
Well, after that, it's a bit of a toss -up. What
do we know? We know that b and c have to appear
before d.
So maybe just to be annoying, I
do a, c, b. That's b. And then d.
So it's a topological order. Notice that things
that are on the left appear in my graph before
things that are on the right, where the word
before here means that there's an edge that points
from one to the other.
By the way, are
topological orderings unique?
No. So if we look at our graph example here,
a, b, c, d is also a topological order.
And what that means is it's somehow very
liberating, right? It means that when we design an
algorithm for finding a topological order, there's
some design decisions that we can make. And we
just have to find
one among many.
But in any event,
we're going to define a slightly different notion
of order. And then we're going to show that
they're closely linked to each
other. And that is the finishing order.
So in the finishing order, we're going to call
full DFS on our graph. Remember, that means we
iterate over all our nodes. And if we haven't
seen that node yet, we call DFS on it.
And now we're going to make an order in which as
soon as the call to a node in that visit function
is complete, meaning I've already iterated over
all my neighbors, then I add my node to the
ordering.
It's like a little bit backward from what we're
used to thinking about. So it's the order in which
full DFS finishes
visiting each vertex.
Yeah? And now here's the claim, is that if we have
a reverse finishing order, meaning that we take
the finishing order and then we flip it backward,
that's exactly going to give us a topological
ordering of the
vertices in our graph.
Right. So let's do that really quickly.
So in other words, our claim here,
I think I'm, yeah, let's see, is
that if I have a directed graph,
so G is a DAG,
then let's see here.
Then,
oops, my notes are backwards. So I should switch
to my adjacent notes, which of course are correct.
Right. So if I have a graph
that's a DAG, then the reverse
of the finishing order
is a topological order.
By the way, we're not going to prove the converse,
that if I have a topological order, that somehow
that thing is the reverse of DFS, at least the
way that maybe I coded it. There's a slightly
different statement, which is, does there exist
a DFS that has that ordering? But that's one that
we'll worry about another time or on
Piazza or whatever. OK. So let's see here.
So we need to prove this thing. So what are we
going to do? Well, what do we need to check is a
topological order is that if I look at any edge
in my graph, it obeys the relationship that I have
on the screen here.
So in particularly, we're going to take the UV
inside of my set of edges. And then what I need
is that U is ordered before V
using the reverse of the finishing
order that we defined here. OK.
So our call to the DFS algorithm,
remember, we call this visit function.
So we have two cases. Either U
is visited before V or it ain't.
So let's do those two cases.
So case number one
is U is visited before V. OK.
All right. So what does that mean? Well, remember
that there's an edge. Like pictorially, what's
going on? Well, there's all kinds of graph stuff
going on. And then there's U. And we know that
there's a directed
edge from U to V.
That's our picture. And maybe there's
other stuff going on outside of V.
So in particular,
well, just by the way that we've defined that visit
function, what do we know? We know that when we
call visit
on U,
well, V is one of its outgoing neighbors. So
in particular, visit on U is going to call
visit V.
And we know that because,
well, U is visited before V.
Right? So currently, V's
parent is none when I get to U.
That make sense?
So after reverse ordering, we're going to have
to keep it in our head. Right? Because now, well,
visit of U called visit of V. So notice that
visit of V has to complete before visit of U.
Right?
V completes
before
visit of U.
Well, so in reverse sorting
in reverse finishing order here, what does that
mean? Well, if this completes before the other guy,
then they get flipped backward in the list, which
is exactly what I want because there's an edge
from U to V.
OK. So case one is done.
Now we have case two,
which is that V is
visited before U.
OK.
So now I'm going to make
one additional observation.
OK, so now I'm going to go back to my other
notes because I like my schematic better.
Right. So what's our
basic picture here?
I don't know.
You know what it was? I printed out another copy
of this. That's OK. I can do it off the top of my
head. OK, so here's my source vertex. His name
is S. Now, there's a bunch of edges and whatever.
There's a long path.
And now, eventually,
what happens? Well,
I have a node V.
And somewhere out there in
the universe is another node U.
And what do I know? I know that by assumption,
I know that there's an edge from U to V.
That make sense? So that's
our sort of picture so far.
OK.
So what do we know? We know that our graph is
acyclic. Yeah, right? Kind of by definition. That's
our assumption.
So can we reach U from V?
In other words, does there
exist a path from V to U?
Right. So that
would look like this.
No, because our graph is acyclic. And I just drew
a cycle. Right. So this is a big X. There's a
frowny face here. Can't do it. He
has hair, unlike your instructor.
OK. So right. So what does this mean? Well, OK,
so by this picture, I suppose, we know that U
cannot be reached from V. Yeah.
So what does that mean? Well, it means that the
visit to V is going to complete and never see U.
Right? Because remember that the visit to V only
ever calls things that are kind of descendants of
V. Right? So in other words,
visit of V completes
without seeing U.
Well, that's exactly the same thing that we
showed in our first case. Right? So by the same
reasoning, what does that mean? In our reverse
finishing order, the ordering from U to V is
preserved. OK. So that sort of completes our
proof here. The reverse finishing order gives me a
topological order,
which is kind of nice.
And so this is a nice, convenient way of taking
all of the nodes in a directed acyclic graph and
ordering them in a way that respects the
topology or the connectivity of that graph.
So we're going to conclude with one final problem,
which I don't have a slide on, but that's OK.
And that's cycle detection. So there's a bit of
an exercise left to the end. So let's do a little
bit of reader here.
So the problem that
we're looking for now is
that we're given
a directed graph.
There's a G in graph,
in case you're wondering.
But now we don't know if it's a DAG or not. And
so the question that we're trying to ask is, does
there exist?
Is there a cycle in our directed acyclic graph? So
we're just given our graph. We want to know, can
we do this?
Let's think through
the logic of this a bit.
So what do we know? We know
that if our graph were a DAG,
then I could call DFS,
get the ordering out, and then I guess flip its
ordering backwards. So I could compute the reverse
finishing order, and it would give
me a topological order of my graph.
So if I were a DAG, I would get a
topological order when I call DFS.
So let's say that I ran DFS.
I got whatever ordering I got. And now I found
an edge that points in the wrong direction. I can
just double check my list of edges, and I find
one that does not respect the relationship that I
see in the second
bullet point here.
Can my graph be a DAG?
No, because if my graph were a DAG, the algorithm
would have worked. I just proved it to you,
right? So if my graph were a DAG, then I could do
a reverse finishing order. And what I would get
back is a topological order. So if I found a
certificate that my order wasn't topological,
something went wrong. And the only thing that could
go wrong is that my graph isn't a DAG. Or yeah,
isn't a DAG. In fact, sort of an exercise left
to the reader and or to your section. Do we still
have section? I
think we do as of now.
Is that this is
an if and only if,
meaning that the only time that you even have a
topological ordering in your graph is if your graph
is a DAG.
This is a really easy fact to sanity check, by the
way. This is not like a particularly challenging
problem. But you should think through it, because
it's a good exercise to make sure you understand
the definitions,
which is to say that if you have a topological
order, your graph is a DAG. If you don't have a
topological order,
your graph isn't a DAG.
So in other words, we secretly gave you an
algorithm for checking if a graph is a DAG at all,
right? What could I do?
Reverse finishing order. Check if it obeys the
relationship on the second bullet point here for
every edge. And if it does, then we're in good
shape. My graph is a DAG. If it doesn't, something
went wrong. And the only thing that could have
gone wrong is not being a DAG. OK. So in other
words, secretly, we just solved,
well, I guess the way that I've written it here,
we've solved the cycle detection problem here,
which is to say that, well, I have a cycle. If
and only if I'm not a DAG, which I can check using
this technique. Of course, the word detection here
probably means that I actually want to find that
cycle, and I haven't told you how to do that
yet. All we know how to do so far is say, like,
somewhere in this graph, there's a cycle, and that's
not so good. So we can do one additional piece
of information in the two minutes we have remaining
to sort of complete our story here, which is to
modify our algorithm ever so slightly to not only
say, like, thumbs up, thumbs down, is there a
cycle in this graph, but also to
actually return the vertices as a cycle.
And the property that we're going to do that, which
is the following, which is that if G contains a
cycle,
then a full DFS will traverse
an edge from a vertex v
to some ancestor of v. I
guess we haven't carefully defined the term ancestor
here. Essentially, if you think of the sort of
the running of the DFS algorithm, then an ancestor
is like something that appears in the recursive
call tree before I got to v.
OK, so how could we prove that?
Well,
let's take a cycle.
And we'll give it a name. In particular,
we'll say that it's a cycle from v0, v1
to vk. And then it's a
cycle, so it goes back to v0.
OK,
and I can order this cycle any
way I want. Notice that if I permute
the vertices in this list in a cyclical way,
meaning that I take the last few of them and stick
them at the beginning of the list, it's still
a cycle. It's a nice thing about cycles.
So in particular,
without loss of generality,
we're going to assume that v0 is
the first vertex visited by DFS.
What does that mean? That means when I do my DFS
algorithm, making all these recursive calls, the
very first vertex to be
touched by this technique is v0.
OK, well, now what's going to end up happening?
Well, think about the recursive call tree starting
at v0.
By the time that completes,
anything that's reachable from v0 is
also going to be complete. Do you see that?
So like, for instance, v0 somewhere
in its call tree might call v1.
And notice that v1 was not
already visited, so in fact, it will.
For v1, I've got to
call v2. And so on.
And in particular,
we're going to get
all the way to vertex k.
So in other words,
we're going to visit
vertex vk.
And notice what's
going to happen.
So remember our algorithm. In fact, we should
probably just put it up on the screen. It would be
easier than talking
about it a bunch.
Well,
vk is now going to iterate over every one
of the neighbors of vk. And in particular,
it's going to see vertex v0.
So we're going to see
the edge from vk to v0, which is an edge by
definition, because we took this to be a cycle here.
But notice that's exactly the thing we set out
to prove, namely that full DFS traverses an edge
from a vertex to one of its ancestors. Here's the
vertex k. Here's its ancestor, v0. Why do we know
that it's an ancestor? Well, because v0 was called
in our call tree before any of these other guys.
So we wanted an algorithm that not only did cycle
detection, but also actually gave me the cycle.
What could I do? Well, it's essentially a small
modification of what we already have. So if I want
to compute topological order or whatever, I can
just do DFS. And that'll tell me, like, yeah or
nay. Does there exist a cycle? If I want to actually
find that cycle, all I have to do is sort of
check that topological order property at the same
time that I traverse the graph during DFS. And
the second that I find an
edge that loops back, I'm done.
And so that's our basic algorithm here. And this
is a technique for actually defining the cycle in
a graph using the DFS algorithm.